Hi, everyone, and welcome back to the MIT class in Urban Energy Systems.
Wherever you're seeing this lecture, please subscribe.
You can either find it on the webpage where you found this video or ask the instructor.
So let's get back to the topic for today, which is going to be cities and decarbonization.
What is the role of cities?
Again, I'm David Su, and if you're thinking about how cities can take action or what are
the roles in decarbonization, you have found the right place and your people.
So I want to cover just briefly how you're going to prepare for class this week.
This is our second class.
I want to make sure that everyone's caught up.
First, the introductory reading from last week is fairly short and skimmable, so it's
easy to catch up, but you should catch up.
And it's particularly important to look at Mackay Chapter 2.
Again, it's Mackay Chapter 2.
There's an initial problem set due Monday night.
You can just access the problem set by going directly to this Google form, the link on
the screen.
You should do the reading for this week.
It's on the syllabus.
I'll also show the reading for this week on the next page.
And then you should watch the rest of this video lecture.
And during the reading and while watching the video lecture, it's important for you
to write down the questions that you have for discussion, and then I want you to feel
free to share them on Slack whenever, asynchronously, or in our class meeting on Tuesday.
So the material for today, again, I won't go over them.
These are all on your syllabus, but these will also be in the slides so you can follow
the links.
The first four readings are the required readings, a kind of gathering of very different readings.
And then the last two readings are optional readings that give additional information
to the articles of us.
So what I want to start with is Mackay Chapter 2, what he calls the balance sheet.
And it's an important set of concepts, simply so we can think about the energy system.
Very simply, what Mackay is trying to do in his book is contrast these red and green bars.
Energy consumption is on the left in red, and energy production is on the right in green.
And so when Mackay titles his book, Sustainable Energy Without the Hot Air, what we're trying
to do is replace our current level of consumption with entirely renewable resources, and that's
how we're going to achieve a sustainable energy system.
And so a sustainable energy system would be if our total conceivable sustainable production
sources on the right are greater than our total consumption, and an unsustainable energy
system would be where our total consumption of energy is larger than our total conceivable
sustainable production.
And of course, these two bars will change over time as our expectations around consumption
change and our technologies and our institutions and our markets for sustainable production
change.
But that's the challenge.
The challenge is to try to put these two in balance and at least have total sustainable
production that is enough to meet all of our societal needs or our global societal needs
for energy consumption.
And so what that might look like is the key forms of consumption on the left-hand stack
in red.
That is the energy we need for transportation, including cars, planes, and freight.
It's the energy we need to heat and cool the spaces that we live in that can wildly differ
across countries.
It's a basic need for lighting so we can see at night.
It's a growing need for energy for information systems and our other gadgets.
The fifth point, food, a tremendous amount of energy goes into growing and transporting
and keeping our food cold and finally manufacturing.
For all the technologies or all the gadgets we need to do transportation or heating and
cooling like information systems and food, we have to make these things in the first
place and that requires a tremendous amount of energy.
On the right-hand side, our sustainable production stack has a number of categories.
The good thing is, and I'll try to emphasize this in the class repeatedly, is that we have
many sustainable technologies that can produce energy.
We have wind and solar.
A solar energy can be harnessed in the form of fortable taillight or solar cells that
produce electricity.
We can harness solar energy through thermal energy and we can also harness solar energy
through biomass by harvesting the potential of the earth to engage in photosynthesis,
the crops that we've been can use for other things, including burning in engines.
Hydroelectric power is producing electricity directly from or mechanical storage directly
from hydropower.
A wave energy and tide energy are two sources of energy that comes from the earth on a regular
basis.
A geothermal energy also comes from the earth.
The heat inside the earth can be harnessed to produce energy, and finally, nuclear.
Mackay puts it with a question mark because it's not clear whether or not nuclear energy
or nuclear power counts are sustainable.
It is low-carbon.
As I said in the earlier class, we have questions about how do we handle the fuel for nuclear
power plants, how do we handle the waste for nuclear power plants, and whether or not that
will be fully sustainable in the long run.
I want to cover two physical concepts from Mackay chapter two that I think are basically
going to be the most important physical concepts you need to understand this class.
The first one, quite simply, is energy.
It's the quantitative property of doing work.
Energy can be neither destroyed nor created, one of our fundamental laws of thermodynamics.
Energy can be transformed into light, heat, or mass, hence the famous equation by Einstein
equals mc squared.
Energy equals mass times the speed of light squared.
This is a fundamental finding out of relativity.
Of course, energy can take many different forms, and we use it in many different forms
in our energy system.
Energy can be kinetic, it can be chemical, we can have potential energy, we can have
mechanical energy, let's say stored in the elastic properties and materials, and of course,
biological energy, which is fundamentally chemical energy, but we have different modes
of perhaps using that chemical energy in our muscles, in animals, in ecosystems.
We're going to measure energy in terms of units of kilowatt hours.
You'll see energy referred to in terms of British thermal units, BTUs, something only
used in the US and America, the United States, of therms, joules, calories, are all units
for energy.
Energy can be converted to kilowatt hours.
A specific category I just want to highlight below is fossil fuels are sometimes measured
in barrels of oil, short tons of coal, cubic feet of natural gas, that's because that's
how we measure the things we trade in commodity markets for commoditized fossil fuels.
But again, the amount of energy in a barrel of oil and a short ton of coal and cubic
foot of natural gas can be converted to kilowatt hours.
So just to give you a few examples, example one, you may have had the frustrating experience
of having gone to the gym, foolishly counting your calories, realizing you worked out for
an hour on a running treadmill as only equivalent to three Oreos.
You can also look at example two, the average American household uses per year about 11,000
kilowatt hours in electricity, each person uses 300 million BTUs total per year, which
is approximately 2.3 gallons of oil, 7.89 pounds of coal and 252 cubic feet of natural
gas per day.
Now it's just worth pointing out that the first example in terms of the American household
is in kilowatt hours, but only counts for electricity.
That's for the whole household per year.
The second sentence measures each person on a per capita basis, but then breaks the millions
of BTUs into different units because of the different sources of energy.
And this is to say that when we do these comparisons, we want to be careful about the units we use,
the averaging over time, and the sources of energy because the original source of energy
may not actually be how much energy we use in the end.
And we'll talk about that more in a few slides.
Another key fiscal concept we have to talk about or will be very useful is power.
And that's the quantitative rate of doing work.
That is, power is energy per time.
It's a rate.
The units we use of that are watts or equal to joules per second.
Other forms of power that you might be familiar with are urges, amperes in terms of electrical
current, horsepower in terms of the engine in your car or other motors, and lumens are
the amount of energy cast off per second from an LED light bulb, but measured over a sphere
around a light bulb.
So it's actually weighted by the area around the light bulb.
Or what degree of area is putting off how much energy.
So to just kind of use the same example as the previous slide, you could say, I worked
out for an hour and I only worked off the equivalent of three Oreos, but maybe sounds
perhaps more impressive if you say my workout maintained a steady power output of three
Oreos per hour.
Another key concept we have to cover that links energy and climate is emissions intensity.
And emissions are measured in terms of greenhouse gases, usually measured in metric ton carbon
dioxide equivalent, which is abbreviated MTCDE or MTCO2E and so on.
And the reason why we have to measure it in terms of metric ton carbon dioxide equivalent
is that there's a lot of different greenhouse gases and some of them, for example, methane
CH4 has much more global warming potential in carbon dioxide.
So a single ton of methane has about 84 times the global warming potential of a ton of carbon
dioxide in early in this life that declines over time to about 20 metric tons of carbon
dioxide equivalent.
So this is just to say that if we have different greenhouse gases, we measure them or make
them all equivalent to a metric ton of carbon dioxide equivalent during their lifetime.
We can also measure emissions intensity by the type of gas, as the example I just gave
you in terms of methane, also nitrous oxide and fluoride hexanes, I think, are another
greenhouse gas.
You can measure emissions intensity per unit of energy.
This much greenhouse gas is created in terms of this much energy.
You can measure greenhouse gases per activity, per dollar GDP or by region.
People use lots of different intensities.
The reason why I want to focus on this key constant intensity is that as we look at
different parts of the system, we're going to look at the intensity of the different
parts of the system to kind of get a whole picture of where greenhouse gases are coming
from, just like we're going to look at energy intensity, in terms of how much energy do
you need for different activities, how much energy do different regions of the world use.
And so to give you a few examples of the components of the parties, the COP meetings that the
UN framework invention on climate change runs every year, they have reporting inventory.
And when every country, which is party to the Paris Agreement, has to report its greenhouse
gas emissions, and frankly, the actions that they're taking to reduce their greenhouse
gases, they have to measure or report their greenhouse gases in terms of a specific inventory
format.
So I've linked to that here.
You can click on it and you can see how countries report different kinds of greenhouse gases.
It's because countries can only see the source of the activities that create greenhouse gases.
So it's easier, of course, to measure how many barrels of oil we burned, or how many
short tons of coal we burned, or let's say how much land use conversion has led to how
much methane or how much carbon dioxide.
We can also measure, let's say, our greenhouse gas emissions per unit of electricity, because
electricity comes from a grid.
The grid is a technology we'll talk about a lot in this class that mixes different sources
of energy together.
And so we try to get an average intensity of greenhouse gas emissions per unit electricity
in different regions.
Another mission's intensity factor that people look at quite often is air quality.
We can look at how many greenhouse gases or how much particulate matter is produced
by certain activities, like vehicle miles traveled or a number of cars in the road.
So just to give you an example of what carbon emission intensity looks like, this is the
carbon emission intensity of economies in 2018, and this is from our world and data.
And you can see, actually, it's measured on the bottom legend here in terms of amount
of kilograms of carbon dioxide equivalent, the carbon dioxide intensity per dollar of
GDP measured in international 2011 prices.
And you can see by that measure, actually, a lot of the developed worlds, such as Australia,
Europe, North America, and Arts of Latin America, don't look very intense, if only because
they don't produce that many greenhouse gases per dollar of a GDP output.
Now, like we talked about in the last class in terms of population, what does this hide?
Well, there's a couple of things with a map, you know, sometimes the area of the map distorts
the actual area or total emissions, you know, small places don't look like they had as much
impact as big places, even though that really has nothing to do with the average.
But the more important point from a map like this is that it hides the fact that the rich
countries like Australia, Europe, North America, and Arts of Latin America simply have much
larger GDPs.
So it looks like the carbon dioxide output per GDP is low.
But if we look at the per capita CO2 emissions, like the point in our last class, you can
see that for a relatively small number of people in those rich developed countries, they have
very high CO2 emissions per capita.
And so your map basically changes biometrically, and you can see the difference between richer
countries and poorer countries.
And overwhelmingly, the richer countries are more responsible for carbon dioxide emissions.
If we look at this similarly in kind of a scatter plot, you can again see that, you know, it looks
like on an emission intensity basis, India and the United States are not that different.
Of course, the differences in terms of the output of the economy on a per capita basis,
the average person in the United States, produces much more and inevitably consumes much more
than your average person in the other Pakistan.
So even though we have equivalent emissions intensity per dollar, we simply produce and
consume much more in the richer countries.
And I make this point because after the Kyoto Protocol, and after the George W. Bush administration
chose to leave the Kyoto Protocol, one of their arguments was that the U.S. actually
had a lower carbon emission intensity or at least a comparable carbon emission intensity
to some developing countries.
Of course, this hid the fact that the United States is both richer and consumes much more
and produces much more.
So that's just a way to talk about what intensities may tell us and what they may hide also.
Now, I'm going to get to a really kind of key diagram that I rather love in this class.
So I'll start off this class by talking about Sankey diagrams.
And you can find a Sankey diagram with the U.S. and every state at this web link at the
bottom, Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory.
What a Sankey diagram is, is basically a flow chart and it's a flow chart between the sources
on the left.
You can see all of our energy sources, solar, nuclear, hydro, wind, geothermal, natural gas
called biomass and petroleum.
And you can see all of the ultimate uses on the right.
And the final, I guess we call final consumption is in residential buildings, commercial buildings,
industrial buildings, and transportation.
Of course, the spinal category here is also a kind of a statement about where does the
energy go in the first place.
Only about 50% of the energy or less that we actually burn in the from the original sources
goes into these uses in these sectors about actually looks like one third of the energy
goes to what we call energy services and rejected energy is the byproduct of that combustion
usually that we don't capture for actual energy services.
So to give you an example, you can see how I said before the electric grid mixes many
different types of energy sources, solar, nuclear, hydro, wind, all these natural gas
and coal all feed into the electric grid.
But when we feed that energy into the electric grid into power plants, we basically only
take a fraction of it looks like about one third of the electricity, one third of the
energy in those energy sources actually goes to things like residential, commercial,
and industrial, but about two thirds of it gets rejected, which means that it's heat
energy going out of each chimney of a coal fire power plant, or might be energy lost
in electric grid, it's simply lost because the resistance of the electrical wires.
And so this kind of graph, I actually find tremendously useful to summarize what the
sources on the left are, the ultimate uses of the energy are on the right, and also
some of the interim steps where we might be able to capture some of the energy back
in terms of energy efficiency, or at least think about how our intermediate technologies
like the electric grid actually use energy and how much of the intrinsic energy in the
fuel source are we using to take one example from this graph.
I think it does a really good job of showing you, for example, that electricity overwhelmingly
goes into residential buildings, commercial buildings and industrial buildings are industrial
activities. But you can see that there's no link between electricity generation and
transportation. So very small orange line here, 0.0.02 quads.
One thing I should have pointed out is that the total US energy consumption in 2021 was
about 97 quads. It's pretty easy mentally to round that up to about 100. So this is
actually 0.02% roughly of all the energy in the US is used, or electricity is used for
transportation. You can see overwhelmingly that the majority of energy for transportation,
24.3 quads, or about 24% of the energy in the US comes from petroleum. And originally
that came from about 35 quads, or 35% of our initial energy sources. And you can see some
portion goes off to industrial activities. But the vast majority of the energy that drives
our transportation system is petroleum. And you can see that when we burn petroleum or
gasoline in our internal combustion engines, a very small fraction that looks like about
20% of it is actually used for moving the car forward. About 80% of the energy actually
goes out of the tailpipe, either in the form of heat out of the tailpipe or else air resistance
that is not really what we're trying to do. We're trying to move goods and services and
people around. And so this is just, again, a way of saying that, you know, there's lots of
different kinds of Sankey diagrams. This is a nice one that has proportional flows between sources,
intermediate, transforming technologies, and uses. It also shows you what efficiency level
is being achieved in these different sectors. This is essentially a counting exercise. Or if
you can find the Sankey diagram for a given region or city or country, it gives you a really good
picture of where the energy is coming from and where the energy is going to. And so we want to
use these Sankey diagrams to think about what our pathways are to deep decarbonization. Deep
decarbonization, I think I've said before, if I haven't said it before, it is both a goal and a
process. We know that climate science tells us that IPCC has told us through an exhaustive scientific
process that we need to achieve net zero anthropogenic greenhouse gas emissions by 2050.
Deep decarbonization is both the goal of getting to net zero emissions by 2050 and also it's this
process. We're decarbonizing for the next 28 years to lessen the effects of climate change.
And so the first deep decarbonization plan started in 2015. The deep decarbonization
pathways project started in 2015 for a number of countries to try to think about what analytical
or policy or technology pathways we needed. It was updated in this paper in 2020 that you read
about this class. That was probably followed by the White House mid-century strategy, which was the
Obama administration's commitment to the Paris Agreement to reduce greenhouse gas emissions
by 80% by 2050. But just four years later, you have a series of reports from academics and NGOs
looking at ways to get the 100% reduction by 2050, which is what the IPCC says we need to do by 2050.
And so the key thing I want to say in this class, but also in the paper I referred to last
time last week of the paper on deep decarbonization that I wrote recently,
is that many of these plans agree with the technology pathways are. So we should focus as
urban policy analysts and urban planners and people who work in cities on implementation,
we should focus on geography, we should focus on politics of it. And frankly, as planners,
we should look at the land use and built environment implications for deep decarbonization.
So look at the Sankey diagram from Williams et al. 2020. They look at the reference case
for energy use in the United States. And this is a reference case that I think the Energy
Information Administration puts out every year. You can see on the left hand side that overwhelmingly
the reference case, which is usually fairly conservative, shows that we will get most of our
energy from we get most of our energy currently from uranium, coal, natural gas, a little bit from
biomass and a large portion of petroleum. You can see renewables here are relatively small,
geothermal, solar, wind and hydro. And all the energy goes through the intermediate steps,
electricity generation, pipeline gas, volume refining outputs, or liquid fuels. It gets
transmitted through the grid. And it ultimately goes to buildings, which are residential and
commercial buildings together. It goes to industry, and it goes to transportation.
Again, you can see here from buildings that overwhelmingly about half of the energy comes
from the grid, half the energy comes from pipeline gas, transportation, almost all the
energy we currently use comes from the petroleum. And industry uses a variety of energy technologies
and fuels. Now let's contrast that with the Williams paper on what a 100% renewable energy
future would look like. There's a couple things to notice here. First, all of our renewables,
the 100% renewable sources we are going to need, are have taken over completely, geothermal, solar,
wind, hydro and biomass. There's no coal, no natural gas and no petroleum. Overwhelmingly,
about two thirds of the energy will go through the electric grid. It will be generated electricity
either go through the grid or you'd be used to produce hydrogen. Hydrogen will produce various
liquid and gaseous fuels. And if you look at what the future looks like in 2050, according to this
paper or this technology pathway, you can see that buildings have to overwhelmingly get their
energy from electricity. Industry will still use a variety of inputs, but all those inputs will be
from intermediate steps that have transformed our renewable energy into the kinds of fuels we
need to drive in ductile processes. And you can see that a transportation is going to come
overwhelmingly from electric, about 50% of our energy in transportation will come from electric.
Some of it will come from I think liquid fuels and some will come from compressed gases such as
hydrogen and maybe natural gas or methane produced from renewable resources. And let's just look at
the implications from this. And this is to read the numbers off those previous two graphs.
And then you look at the power sector, you can see the petroleum, natural gas and coal, as I said,
have to be eliminated completely, 100%. Biomass has to grow by three and a half times. Nuclear
power in the 100% renewable case is actually eliminated completely because I think Williams
and I'll do not define nuclear as a renewable energy source. But the key things that most
dire I think are most challenging things we have to deal with are growing our solar energy
share by about a factor of 46. We have to grow our share per wind by a factor of 27. Hydro and
geothermal are going to be relatively small players in this forecast. And that's just the
electric power sector. If you look at buildings, residential, commercial, you can see two things.
Not only does electricity have to decline in total use, but we have to completely eliminate
natural gas. And we have to increase our use of biomass just slightly. And the key thing is that
the reason why we're declining our total use of electricity is that it's more efficient.
But at the same time, the electricity we do use is going to be used to do things that natural gas
currently does. If we're going to get heating and cooling from electricity, rather than natural gas,
as we do now. And so this is one important point I want to highlight from Sankey Diagrams.
If you look at the total primary energy in buildings, it actually has to go down by about 50%.
And this is the point I think I made in the last class, which is if you look back here,
the total amount of energy looks like I think roughly 100 plots, also 100 exajoules, I think
is how this paper measures it. And if you look at the next slide, you can see that the width of
these flows have gone down by a bit, which is to make the point that I think I said to you last
week, which is that not only do our uses have to become more efficient, we also have to simply
reduce the total amount we're using. And the remaining 50% has to become renewable. So we
actually need a complete transformation of our energy system, both on the consumption side and
production side. If you look at the Tong paper, this is going to shift a little bit to this question
of existing energy infrastructure. This is a paper written in 2019 in Nature. And in this paper,
they say our estimate suggests that little or no new CO2 emitting infrastructure can be commissioned
and that existing infrastructure may need to be retired early or be retrofitted with carbon
capture and storage technology in order to meet the Paris agreement climate goals. So this paper
is basically going to show us that we have existing infrastructure, obviously the energy
infrastructure that we use every day. And if you want to meet our Paris agreement climate goals,
which is keeping preferably global average temperatures less than 1.5 degrees Celsius higher
than pre-industrial era, we actually need to build no more fossil fuel infrastructure, which is CO2
emitting infrastructure. And we may have to retire some of the energy infrastructure that we have
early before it's planned lifetime. This is part of the struggle. This is why you have activists
trying to retire whole fired power plants and avoid building new pipelines in natural gas plants
or having passing, let's say, gas bans for new appliances in parts of Massachusetts and California
and other states. So just to show you what this looks like, all these categories in the legend
here, commercial buildings, residential building, international transport, road transport, industry
electricity, these kinds of technologies have a natural lifetime in terms of they have a committed
CO2 emission from existing and proposed infrastructure. And you can see that our existing
infrastructure is overwhelmingly dominated by industry and electricity and road transport
is this blue wedge and buildings are actually relatively small. And those are all things that
are going to phase out naturally over time because infrastructure gets old. If you don't
maintain it and you don't rebuild it, then it wears out and you can't use it anymore. We have
more proposed infrastructure, but that proposed infrastructure cannot be built if we need to
try to meet our price of climate goals. At the same time, in the B panel here, we have the committed
emissions from different countries. And you can see the lifetime of infrastructure in China is
relatively long and a large portion of the future problem because so much of it is built fairly
recently. You can see the rest of the world is actually only about two thirds of the problem
that China poses. And actually, the US has a relatively small future committed emissions
because of the nature of our technology. Of course, there's been many more proposed projects,
but the point of this paper is that we cannot actually build the proposed infrastructure. And
we may have to retire some of this existing infrastructure early to avoid going over our
climate limits. So another kind of interesting graph in this paper, which I like quite a bit,
is a population pyramid. But instead of a population pyramid showing the proportions of
the population of people by age, it actually shows the age structure of our global electricity
generating capacity. And I want to simply make a point about what the different nature of the
problem in China and the US are. You can see on the left hand side, this is the rest of the world,
but in some ways, dominated by the US. You can see on 15 or 17 years ago, we built quite a bit
of natural gas or oil infrastructure. You can see the rest of the world has more recently
been building gas and oil infrastructure at the yellow bars. And you can see on the right hand
side, this is an electricity generation from coal that is overwhelmingly dominated by coal
fire power plants built in China, mostly the last 12 or 14 years. The reason why we use this
graph is to look at the nature of the problem and what particular sectors we're going to have to
tackle, which particular power plants are going to have to tackle, to avoid creating more greenhouse
gas emissions. That again, will put us beyond our Paris agreement targets, that will then finally
jeopardize the climate of the planet. So this brings me to cities, which is numerous recent
studies show that most US greenhouse gas emissions or global greenhouse gas emissions in
some of these studies are from cities. But the key point of this literature on a highlight is that
the exact proportion depends on how and where you count. The Jones et al. 2018 paper and the
Goldstein et al. 2020 paper, both find that higher incomes and lower population densities are highly
correlated with higher carbon footprints and energy use. The Gurney et al. 2018, 2020, and 2021
reports and papers find that a majority of road and fossil fuel infrastructure or use
can be associated with cities. The Moran paper is quite interesting and it finds that both in the
China, in both in China and the US, the largest 10 cities plus 5% or the top 5% of suburban
residents by income are responsible for more than a majority of the greenhouse gas emissions
from both countries, China and the US. Which is to say that if we focused just on the largest
10 cities and the most carbon intensive suburbs, then we could actually make a significant difference
in the greenhouse gas emissions in countries. It is also kind of recapping the moral argument I
made to you in the last class, which is that the richest people in both countries have a
disproportionate responsibility to lower the greenhouse gas emissions just in the same way
that the US has a disproportionate responsibility to lower greenhouse gas emissions relative to the
rest of the world. Finally, the CEDO in the 2021 and the Weidman et al. papers 2021 kind of show
different research and planning frameworks for how do you really count these greenhouse gas
emissions. And so there's debate about how you count it, but there's this emerging consensus
in the literature that cities are responsible for a large portion of greenhouse gas emissions
in many countries, including China and the US. Just to highlight a few of the key issues why
it's hard to get an exact proportion depends on different definitions of cities or what an urban
area is. It depends which emissions you count, upstream emissions like things that you import in
the form of fuels or goods, downstream emissions, the things that you export out of the city or waste
energy or waste products that go outside the city and goods and services. There's all different
ways to count the emissions from all these things. The C40 and air purport that I assigned in the
reading gets to some of these issues. Finally, some interesting questions that are not always
accounted for. Cities clearly shape local microclimates. Do we count that as part of climate
change because that actually changes how people subsequently use energy in cities? And this is
kind of a fundamental question. How do you measure affluence? Do you measure in terms of wealth or
income? I suspect if we measure these in different ways, you'd find different places are responsible
for different levels of greenhouse gas emissions. Just to again kind of make this argument about
how we measure things matters and also how intensity may show us a different picture.
This is from the Gurney et al. 2020 paper. The left hand panel shows absolute emissions.
You can see the absolute emissions in this country basically almost identically mimics
the spatial or urban spatial structure of the country where all the red areas and the
left coast are high concentrations of absolute emissions. Of course, if you make it on a per
capita basis, you might say, okay, out west people are relatively inefficient. But we should also
highlight the fact that there's these interrelationships between these two areas. Places out here in
the west is a high concentration of fossil fuel production generation. But where is that energy
going? That energy is going to cities. And so if we think back to Mackay's left hand bar of
consumption, I would argue to all the urban planners in the room, and I have said this to
my colleagues in city government, that we should not be complacent about the fact that we think
we have relatively low per capita emissions in cities. We have to be responsible for the fact
that energy is being used elsewhere, that we consume in the form of fuels, goods and services,
food, and we export our waste also. So that is the place where cities can have a big impact on
greenhouse gas emissions. But it may be a different kind of efficiency. We might have to think about
how much we consume, why we consume energy, and how do we do it more efficiently, and hopefully
ultimately reduce our consumption to meet our decarbonization goals. Finally, I'll just flash
through the readings quickly because we'll talk about them more in class. The Sue et al. 2019
paper, this is actually not my paper. It's written by a colleague, Angel Sue at the University of
North Carolina. It is a research roadmap for how do we spend more time or how do we spend more
thinking about quantifying the climate mitigation actions that non-state or subnational governments
could take? And this is getting that kind of measurement question. How are we going to measure
greenhouse gas emissions and how are we going to measure what action those energies take?
And just to give you an example, there's different ways to count how cities
take climate action in comparison to state targets. And those targets may be different
still than national level targets. And so, you know, this is the question, are we going to double
count? In some cases, cities are actually most cases, cities are more ambitious than their states.
Cities are all more ambitious than national governments. We want to avoid double counting.
We want to count cities considering how we're going to, those cities are going to act
relative to cities without targets. So this paper, we'll get at that. We'll just talk about more in
class. And this brings me to this optional reading by Mark Ulth et al, which is pledges and progress.
This is a Brookings institutional report. It looks at the hundred largest cities across the United
States. They find that number of cities, these hundred cities have all set fairly ambitious
goals. Everything on the blue here on the right, the parentheses shows you when they set the goal.
And you can see Boston where we are. Actually, Cambridge is also in the graph somewhere. But
Boston, Massachusetts in 2005, so they're going to have an 80% reduction by 2050. As all of these
cities did, also meeting the White House's targets in 2016, it's commensurate with the
national targets 2016. You can see a number of these cities here and left have set less ambitious
targets, 50% reduction, let's say 40% reduction, but they may have more closer targets. So this
might be an interim goal on the way to a more ambitious target down the road. But the take
home from this Mark Ulth report and I'll let you look at your lead here because I think
somebody will be quite interested in particular cities. You can see what the difference is
between their current emissions inventory and their target emissions. And you can see in the
case of Chicago, Illinois, they set a 2015, they have a 2015 greenhouse gas inventory.
They have a target emission in the year that inventory. And it looks like Chicago is emitting
about 50% more emissions than they targeted in 2015. I actually find this report quite hopeful
because it takes a serious look at all these cities and says, well, we should take cities
seriously in terms of the climate action goals and studying. But in order to take them seriously,
we also have to hold them according to the plans that they're setting. So it looks like Boston
is closer to its target at 10% higher inventory emissions than it had planned for in 2016.
That 10% hopefully gives us or that inventory difference gives us a good place to target our
actions. Other places, let's say Los Angeles looks like it's actually ahead of its goals. It's
actually 10% less in terms of greenhouse gas emissions than they planned for in 2013. So
cities looks like almost overwhelmingly temperate cities except for Minneapolis,
but all these fairly temperate region cities are doing better than they expected.
Some of these cities here, I guess Chicago is a cold climate city and Tucson is the opposite.
But for different reasons, Tucson and Chicago are wildly over the goals they set in 2014 and 2015.
And so I'll just stop here and we'll talk more in class this week. We'll talk about the results
of our carbon calculators that we did for homework. I'll put some questions for discussion on the
board and we'll just start our discussion. And we'll have some news items to talk about in class.
Thank you very much. I hope you guys have a great rest of your weekend.